18 theut WASTE NO TIME" Of course Mary did not waken early the next morning. She
slept late because she was tired, and when Martha brought her breakfast she
told her that though Colin was quite quiet he was ill and feverish as he
always was after he had worn himself out with a fit of
crying. Mary ate her breakfast slowly as she listened. "He says he wishes they would
please go and see him as soon as they can," Martha said. "It's queer what a fancy
he's took to thee thou did give it him last night for sure— —didn't thou Nobody
else would have dared to do it hey poor lad! He's been spoiled till salt won't
save him. Mother says as the two worst things as can happen to a child is never
to have his own way— —or always to have it.
She doesn't know which is the worst thou was in a fine temper th s too. But he
says to me when I went into his room, 'Please ask Miss Mary if she'll please
come and talk to me?' Think of him saying please! Will you go, Miss?" "I'll run and see
first," said Mary. "No, I'll go and see Colin first and tell him— —I know what I'll tell
him," with a sudden inspiration. She had her hat on when she
appeared in Colin's room and for a second he looked disappointed. He was in bed and his face
was pitifully white and there were dark circles around his
eyes. "I'm glad you came," he said. "My head aches and I ache all over because I'm so
tired. Are you going somewhere?" Mary went and leaned against his
bed. "I won't be long," she said. "I'm going to Dicken but I'll come back. Colin, it's—
—it's something about the secret garden." His whole face brightened and a little color came into
it. "Oh! is it!" he cried out. "I dreamed about it all night. I heard you say something
about gray changing into green, and I dreamed I was standing in a place all
filled with trembling little green leaves— —and there were birds on nests
everywhere and they look so soft and still. I'll lie and think about it until you come
back." In 5 minutes Mary was with Dickon in their garden. The fox and the crow
were with him again and this time he had brought two tame
squirrels. "I came over on the pony this morning he said. "Eh! he is a good little
chap— —Jump is! I brought these two in my pockets. This here one he's called Nut
and this here other one's called Shell."
When he said "Nut" one squirrel leapt onto his right shoulder and when he said
"Shell" the other one leapt onto his left shoulder. When they sat down on the grass
with Captain curled at their feet Su solemnly listening on a tree a Nut and
Shell no noing about close to them, it seemed to Mary that it would be scarcely
bearable to leave such delightfulness, but when she began to tell her story somehow the look in
dickens's funny face gradually changed her mind. She could see he felt sorrier
for Colin than she did. He looked up at the sky and all about him. "Just listen to
them birds the world seems full of them all whistling and piping he said. "Look at
them darting about and hearken at them calling to each other. Come springtime
seems like as if all the world's calling The leaves is uncurling so you can see
him and my word the nice smells there is about!" sniffing with his happy Turned Up
nose and that poor lad lying shut up and seeing so little that he gets to
thinking of things as sets him screaming Eh! my wean get him out here wean get him
watching and listening and sniffing up the air and get him just soaked through
with sunshine and we m not lose no time about it." When he was very much
interested he often spoke quite broad Yorkshire though at other times he tried
to modify his dialect so that Mary could better understand. But she loved his
broad Yorkshire and had in fact been trying to learn to speak it
herself. So she spoke a little now I that wean she said (which meant "Yes, indeed, we
must"). "I'll tell the what I will do first," she proceeded, and dickan grinned, because
when the little wench tried to twist her tongue into speaking Yorkshire it amused
him very much. "He's took a gradely fancy to thee. He wants to see thee and he
wants to see suot and Captain. When I go back to the house to
talk to him I'll ask him if they can I come and see him tomorrow morning and
bring that creatures with the and then— —in a bit, when there's more leaves out
and happen a bu or two, we'll get him to
come out and that she'll push him in his chair and we'll bring him here and show him
everything." When she stopped she was quite proud of herself. She had never
made a long speech in Yorkshire before and she had remembered very
well the and talk a bit of Yorkshire like that to Mr col
Dickon chuckled they'll make him laugh and there's not as good for ill folk as
Laughing is. Mother says she believes as halfer hour's good laugh every morning
you cure a chap as was making ready for typhus fever." "I'm going to talk Yorkshire to him
this very day," said Mary, chuckling herself. The garden had reached the time
when every day and every night it seemed as if Magicians were passing through it
drawing loveliness out of the earth and the boughs with
wands. It was hard to go away and leave it all, particularly as Nut had actually
crept onto her dress and Shell had scrambled down the trunk of the apple
tree they sat under and stayed there looking at her with inquiring
eyes. But she went back to the house and when she sat down close to Colin's bed
he began to sniff as Dickon did though not in such an experienced way. "You smell
like flowers and— —and fresh things," he cried out quite
joyously. "What is it you smell of? It's cool and warm and sweet all at the same
time." "It's the wind from the mo said Mary.
"It comes to sitting on the grass under a tree with Dickon and with Captain and
Soot and Nut and Shell. It's the springtime and outer doors and sunshine as smells so
greatly She said it as broadly as she could, and you do not know how broadly
Yorkshire sounds until you have heard someone speak it. Colin began to
laugh. "What are you doing?" he said. "I never heard you talk like that before. How funny it
sounds." "I'm giving thee a bit of Yorkshire," answered Mary
triumphantly. "I cannot talk as greatly as Dickon and Martha can but thou sees I
can shape a bit. Doesn't thou understand a bitter Yorkshire when thou hears it
and thou a Yorkshire lad thyself bred and born! Eh! I wonder thou not ashamed of
thy face." And then she began to laugh too and they both laughed until they could
not stop themselves and they laughed until the room echoed and Mrs. Medlock
opening the door to come in drew back into the corridor and stood listening
amazed. "Well, upon my word!" she said, speaking rather broad Yorkshire herself
because there was no one to hear her and she was so astonished. "Whoever heard the
like! Whoever on earth would have thought it!" There was so much to talk about. It
seemed as if Colin could never hear enough of Dickon and Captain and suot
and Nut and Shell and the pony whose name was Jump. Mary had run round into
the wood with Dickon to see Jump. He was a tiny little shaggy Mo pony
with thick locks hanging over his eyes and with a pretty face and a nuzzling velvet
nose. He was rather thin with living on more grass but he was as tough and wiry
as if the muscle in his little legs had been made of steel
springs. He had lifted his head and winned softly the moment he saw Dickon
and he had trotted up to him and put his head across his shoulder and then Dickon
had talked into his ear and Jump had talked back in odd little winnies and
puffs and snorts. Dickon had made him give Mary his small front hoof and kiss
her on her cheek with his velvet muzzle. "Does he really understand
everything Dickens says?" Colin asked. "It seems as if he does," answered Mary. "Dickon
says anything will understand if you're friends with it for sure, but you have to be friends for
sure." Colin lay quiet a little while and his strange gray eyes seemed to be
staring at the wall, but Mary saw he was thinking. "I wish I was friends with
things," he said at last, "but I'm not. I never had anything to be friends with,
and I can't bear people." "Can't you bear me?" asked Mary. "Yes, I can," he answered. "It's very
funny but I even like you." "Ben Weatherstaff said I was like him,"
said Mary. "He said he'd warrant we'd both got the same nasty tempers. I think
you're like him too. We all three alike— —you and I I and Ben Weatherstaff. He said
we were neither of us much to look at
and we were as sour as we looked. But I
don't feel as sour as I used to before I knew the robin and
Dickon." "Did you feel as if you hated people?" "Yes," answered Mary without any
affectation. "I should have detested you if I had seen you before I saw the robin and
Dickon." Colin put out his thin hand hand and touched
her. "Mary," he said, "I wish I hadn't said what I did about sending Dickon
away. I hated you when you said he was like an angel and I laughed at you but—
—but perhaps he is." "Well, it was rather funny to say it,"
she admitted frankly, "because his nose does turn up and he has a big mouth and
his clothes have patches all over them and he talks broad Yorkshire, but—
—but if an angel did come to Yorkshire and live on the moall if there was a Yorkshire
angel— —I believe he'd understand the green things and know how to make them
grow and he would know how to talk to the wild creatures as Dicken does and
they'd know he was friends for sure." "I shouldn't mind dickan looking at me," said
Colin; "I want to see him." "I'm glad you said that," answered Mary, "because— —because—"
Quite suddenly it came into her mind that this was the minute to tell him.
Colin knew something new was coming.
"Because what?" he cried eagerly. Mary was so anxious that she got up from her
stool and came to him and caught hold of both his hands. "Can I trust you? I trusted
Dickon because birds trusted him. Can I trust you— —for sure— for sure she implored.
Her face was so solemn that he almost whisper whispered his answer. "Yes— —yes!"
"Well, Dickon will come to see you tomorrow morning, and he'll bring his
creatures with him." "Oh! Oh!" Colin cried out in delight. "But that's not all," Mary went
on, almost pale with solemn excitement.
"The rest is better. There is a door into the garden. I found it. It is under the
ivy on the wall." If he had been a strong healthy boy Colin would probably have
shouted "Hooray! Hooray! Hooray!" but he was weak and rather hysterical; his eyes grew
bigger and bigger and he gasped for breath. "Oh! Mary!" he cried out with a half
sob. "Shall I see it? Shall I get into it?
Shall I live to get into it?" and he clutched her hands and dragged her
toward him. "Of course you'll see it!"
snapped Mary indignantly. "Of course you'll live to get into it! Don't be silly!"
And she was so unhy sterical and natural and childish that she brought him to his
senses and he began to laugh at himself and a few minutes afterward she was
sitting on her stool again telling him not what she imagined the secret garden
to be like but what it really was, and Colin's aches and tiredness were
forgotten and he was listening in raptured It is just what you thought it
would be," he said at last. "It sounds just
as if you had really seen it. You know I said that when you told me
first." Mary hesitated about 2 minutes and then boldly spoke the
truth. "I had seen it— —and I had been in,"
she said. "I found the key and got in weeks ago. But I didn't tell you— —I D
because I was so afraid I couldn't trust you— for